The first pilgrim is an Oseram who seeks to visit
the Shrine of Kings on the road to the city.
He waits there now, forbidden to enter by an old Sun Priest who'll suffer no heathen.
This Utaru lost her companion on the edge of the Jewel
at a pool where Snapmaws gather.
And the Banuk would paint a mark on the Sun's Climb,
a call to the machine spirits I understand.
They need no beckoning.
So, clear the machines out of two shrines and move a priest out of the other.
All I can ask for is your charity and that their stories are heard.
Namman, rituals and prayers can't bring back those who are lost.
No, but it can help those who grieve to find themselves.
It can lend them strength and hope, like a new sunrise.
[Carja artisan]
I swore I'd ask her to marry me on a sunny day. Hope her father says yes.
[Carja guard]
If you wander into the outlands south of here,
pray to the Sun you never run into a Thunderjaw called Redmaw.
[Carja artisan]
Oh, that's nice. Glad I stopped for a bit.
I've seen this four times already.
This must be the Shrine of Kings that Namman told me about.
[Oseram worker]
Every time I go near the statue, he shouts at me.
Oseram slaves built that thing. We deserve to have a look.
[Oseram worker]
It may have been meant for the Mad Sun-King, but it's ours.
You won't get in there.
That dried up old prune in a robe sees to that.
I can be persuasive.
But what does an Oseram want with a Carja shrine anyway?
It reminds me of someone,
gone two years now.
But what does a girl like you know of loss?
Try me.
I had a lover,
worked on monuments to their bastard king.
Then he gave them a show in their Sun Ring for good measure.
The Carja gave me back his broken bones.
But what use are they?
They won't build again.
They won't make me smile.
And seeing a statue of the Mad Sun-King will?
I need to see his work again.
The marks his hands carved.
The set of the metals they hammered.
That's the soul of him.
But that shriveled up old priest won't let me near it.
I'll see what I can do.
[Oseram worker]
Every time I go near the statue, he shouts at me!
Oseram slaves built that thing. We deserve to have a look.
[Oseram worker]
It may have been meant for the Mad Sun-King, but its ours now.
It's a public monument, not his private shrine.
Turn away, child.
The Abiding Jahamin wishes to be alone in his retreat.
If you want to be alone, go someplace else.
Others want to pray here.
Defile it, you mean.
Yet another debasement of what was once pure.
Truly, our tribe has lost the light.
Our king is false.
Our temple is corrupt.
And our soldiers weak.
The Sun hastens across the sky for shame.
So the Carja have become impure?
What does that even mean?
Is Meridian not meant for those who built it?
Who made it great?
It was pure before outlander squatters took it over.
You mean Meridian was pure when the outsiders
were in cages or dying in your arena?
The Sun is pure, child.
It is not our place to question Its divine will, only to act upon it.
I thought Avad taking the throne was the Sun's will?
The boy dishonored his father.
Dishonored us all.
To kill the Sun-King.
What shadow, what twilight time he brought upon us.
And how many more would the Mad Sun-King have killed if Avad hadn't stopped him?
The Sun called for blood.
There was no choice but to obey.
Why do you think your army is weak?
Because you're not at war with everyone?
A Carja throne relying on forge-dirt mercenaries? Preposterous!
The so-called liberation was nothing but a purge.
Our most blessed warriors chased out of the city,
exiled to Sunfall and the Forbidden West.
Our tribe is torn.
The ones who walked in light now go by shadow.
And yet everyone but you seems happy they're gone.
They call themselves Sun Priests.
But they have no authority, youths and sycophants all.
Yet those who gave their whole lives to the Sun's service are shamed and ignored.
So that's what this is.
A tantrum, a cry for attention?
You know nothing of our rites, and yet you dare to insult me?
I'm done arguing with you.
Stay or go, but I won't allow you to keep others away.
I am here by the will of the Sun.
If you won't accept change, you should try to make peace with it.
Your bitterness has poisoned you.
I have no need of your pity.
I wasn't offering it.
But if you step aside, you can keep your pride.
Since it's so important to you.
My conviction blazes like the noonday light.
Then stop me from bringing in the Oseram.
I… I cannot.
I thought so.
You don't believe in the throne, the priesthood, the army, or the city.
So I guess you have no authority here.
I have the authority of the Sun!
Then call it for help.
No one else will listen.
There'll be a reckoning.
You'll back away from it.
[Oseram worker]
The wheel turning all day. By the forge, I believe I've earned a drink or two.
He gave them the best work he'd ever do.
Carja carving is fancy, finicky work.
They've thin fingers, you see.
Not like forge-burned hands. And look at it now.
They defaced it because they hated what it stood for.
They defaced a thing slaves like him lived and died for.
Slaves they've already forgotten.
Short sighted bastards the lot.
If they thought their Sun set off this bridge, they'd jump after it.
I thank you for honouring my wish.
I hope you can find peace.
I wouldn't know what to do with it. Any more than the Carja do.
[Oseram worker]
Never bothered me that the Carja talk down to us.
I'm supposed to take someone dressed like that seriously?
[Carja guard]
Watch out for the Oseram merchants.
[Carja outlander]
…I should report it to the Sun Court.
The machine saw me.
This must be the Sun's Climb where the Banuk wants to paint his mark.
[Banuk]
It's good you did this.
You were a better hunter than I.
I'll paint the mark while the spirits of the Glinthawks linger.
There will be more where they came from.
Yes, there will always be more machines.
Their spirits find new bodies.
But we only last a long as memory.
That's why I must leave the story.
A monument to our vanished Shamans, to the wisdom the Carja bled from us.
The machine oil in the paint will preserve it.
Preserve their memory against all that was cut away.
You have my thanks, hunter.
Looking good.
This is where the Utaru wanted to say her goodbyes.
When we fled from our cages during the liberation
I tore through this clearing thinking my friend was behind me.
I kept running, but here she remains.
Thank you for making it safe for me to return.
I don't want to rush you, but it won't stay safe for long.
I understand.
I've done this before in waking dreams.
In the pool I'll find the bracelet of seeds she dropped when she fell.
The seeds will be split, escaped, grown wild.
She's passing from my memory into the jungle's.
I'll tell her it was I who died here and became a stranger in our own land.
And she who still lives in every time of planting, of rains, harvest… oh!
What is it?
There. Her bracelet.
And I thought she was behind me.
But there's only my reflection.
Do you need to be alone?
For the first time I am.
Looks good.
I'll find a use for you.
Keep that for later.
Aloy, you're a woman of your word.
Olin.
Your family.
I saw the threat from Helis.
You have a wife and young boy?
If I'd have striven to keep them safe instead of all I've done.
This is your chance, Olin.
That's why we're here.
I'll take it.
A kinder deal was never struck.
They're being held close by?
Yes, the farmstead just beyond these rocks.
I'll take you.
[Olin]
That's it, nestled against the Spurflints.
Best not to think about the previous owners.
[Aloy]
Too late.
[Olin]
Aloy, down behind this rock.
So this is it.
I can't bear being so close, and yet…
You've been watching for a while.
What's the best way in?
You think if I had a head for strategy, either of us would be in this mess?
Fair point.
We could storm the front gate, Oseram style.
How many Eclipse are we talking?
From what I've seen a fair few.
Well armed and armoured.
Bowmen watching from the ridges.
But there's no space for their machine demons.
With the Eclipse, there's always another blade at your back.
So I'll watch yours if you'll let me.
No, you wait here.
Be ready to follow when the fighting stops.
Oh, I'll be ready.
This has to be where they're holding Olin's family.
Bolted tight. One of the Eclipse must have the key.
[Eclipse cultist]
To me, brothers!
You cannot run from righteousness!
[Eclipse cultist]
Where? We were just getting started.
Die!
Come on, come on.
We heard the commotion outside.
You're not one of them.
Who are you?
Don't be afraid.
I'm going to get you out of here.
I hadn't given up on hope, but I'd forgotten the taste of it.
Is it safe for us to leave?
The Eclipse won't be stopping you.
I dreamed of escape, a thousand different ways.
But all of them put my son at risk.
You survived, you protected him, that's what matters.
Now, your husband's waiting for you.
Olin!
I heard the fighting stop!
You brought him back to us.
Thank you.
There's no need to thank me.
I have much to confess.
I accepted a devil's bargain, and others paid the price.
And do you think I don't know?
I heard them talk.
You know there's always been dirt on my hands.
Now there's blood too.
Take your son up in those hands.
Come back to The Claim with us.
You should listen to your wife, Olin.
But Helis and his demons…?
I am honour bound to help you, Aloy.
With what little honour a dicer like me has.
Olin,
whatever your debts, you don't owe them to me now.
Go with your family.
Show them you're a better man.
Farewell, Aloy.
Your mother.
I hope you find her before they do.
Here they come.
There's the Tallneck that my Focus picked up.
Have to climb up to the Tallneck's head.
Hello!
Deal with him quick.
I think I'm in the clear.
I think I can leap onto the Tallneck from here.
Gotta follow up!
Alright, now I just have to reach its head.
There, got it!
Oh, come on.
Ah, better.
Low and quiet does it.
This'll help.